A Guide to the Papers of the Allen Family 1825-1953
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Allen Family, 1825-1953
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9780
This collection contains ca. 70 pieces in one Hollinger box.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was presented as a gift to the Library by Mark C. Riley on January 27, 1972.
Scope and Content Information
This collection, 1825-1953, consists chiefly of correspondence in the 1850's from the Allen family to John J. Allen, Jr., while he was in Texas. There is also correspondence between the family and Henry C. Allen and Robert E. Allen while they were students at the University of Virginia. There is much valuable commentary on contemporary political and social themes, but the strength of this collection lies in the insight it lends to the study of a family unit in the 1850's.
Arrangement
The collection has been single foldered and arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Typed copy of grants to Lafayette and letter of acknowledgement 1825 January 1
- James Allen to John P. Allen 1829 February 9, Typescript
- James Allen to John J. Allen, Sr. 1830 July 3, Typescript
- James Allen to John Allen, Sr. 1832 December 24, Typescript
- James Allen to John J. Allen, Sr. 1834 November 10, Typescript
- James Allen to John J. Allen, Sr. 1836 June 14, Typescript
- Henry C. Allen to John J. Allen 1851 October 23, ALS, w/typescript
- Jane to "Dear Cousin" 1851 October, ALS
- Jane to "Dear Cousin" 1852 January 13, ALS
- Robert E. Allen to John Allen and Mary E. P. to John Allen 1852 February 21 and 23, ALS
- Wm. W. Gwathmey to R. B. Doswell 1854 November 23, ALS w/typescript
- Mary E. P. Allen to John J. Allen, Jr. 1854 December 28, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen 1855 February 1, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 March 6, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 March 15, ALS
- Mary Jane Allen Watts to John J. Allen 1855 March 17, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 April 27, ALS
- John J. Allen, Sr. to John J. Allen, Jr. 1855 April 27, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen and John Allen, Sr. to John Allen, Jr. 1855 June 13, 2 ALS
- John J. Allen, Sr. to John J. Allen, Jr. 1855 July 16, ALS w/typescript
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 July 16, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 August 13, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 September 17, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 November 2, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen 1855 November 6, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 November 8, ALS
- Mary Jane Allen Watts to Mary E. P. Allen 1855 December 8, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1855 December 12, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John J. Allen 1855 December 14, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 February 19, ALS w/incomplete typescript
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 February 20, ALS
- G. J. Allen to John Allen 1856 March 1, ALS w/typescript
- James Madison Allen to John Allen 1856 March 1, ALS
- Baldwin Allen to John Allen and Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 March 1 and March 3, 2 ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 March 3, Typescript
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen 1856 March 15, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 March 27, ALS
- Evaline Allen to John Allen 1856 April 28, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 July 9, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John J. Allen 1856 July 19, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen 1856 August 8, ALS w/typescript
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 August 8, ALS w/typescript
- John J. Allen, Sr. to John J. Allen, Jr. 1856 August 12, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 October 4, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1856 October 9, ALS
- Henry C. Allen to John Allen 1856 December 7, ALS
- John J. Allen, Sr. to John J. Allen, Jr. 1857 February 20, ALS
- John W. Allen to John Allen 1857 May 13, ALS w/typescript
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1857 May 29, ALS
- Mary E. P. Allen to John Allen 1858 June 2, ALS
- J. B. Stovall to "Dear Mother" 1861 October 23, ALS
- J. A. Payne to Russell H. Allen 1925 February 24, TLS
  Contains genealogical information regarding the descendents of John George Jackson and Mary Payne Jackson.
- Sallie Maxwell Bennett to Mrs. John J. Bland 1938 June 14, ALS
- ( ? ) to John J. Allen, III 1938 June 15, TL carbon
- Margaret Cheney to Mary 1938 June 20, ALS
  Contains genealogical information.
- Genealogical chart of descendents of Robert Allen and Lady (Mary or Alice) Walkinshaw 1938
- E. P. Waller to General Robert H. Allen 1940 March 13, TL Carbon
- Letter from Library of Congress to Miss Cornelia M. Allen 1953
  Regarding the four letters she presented to the library.
- Dr. Herfs Prescription for Dysentery n.d.
- Chart showing descendants of Col. William Watts and Mary Jane Allen n.d.
- Three photographs of John G. Jackson, one of Maj. Alfred H. Jackson, one of Jonathan Jackson n.d.
- Two photographs of unidentified persons n.d.
- Genealogical information concerning the Allen family n.d.